Guide to the James Joseph Daly Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Joseph Daly papers
1916-1949
YCAL MSS 649
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.05
(11 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and professional activity of poet and playwright James Joseph Daly. Correspondence in the collection consists chiefly of incoming correspondence from writers, journal editors, publishers, and others, but also includes drafts and carbons of outgoing letters and writings and enclosures. Correspondents include Elizabeth Ames at Yaddo, Kenneth Burke, John Cheever, Padraic Colum, Malcolm Cowley at The New Republic, James T. Farrell, Robinson Jeffers, Alfred Kreymborg, Haniel Long, Archibald MacLeish, Henry Miller, Kenneth Rexroth, Lennox Robinson, and Thornton Wilder. Writings in the collection include drafts of plays, poems, and other writings, such as short essays, sketches, scenes of plays, reviews, notes, and school papers. Personal papers feature notebooks and material relating to the theater, including manuscript material, correspondence, and printed materials, such as playbills and clippings.
Daly, James Joseph, 1901-1945
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Margo Perkins on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James Joseph Daly (1901-)
The poet and playwright James Joseph Daly was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania and educated at the Carnegie Institute of Technology and at Harvard University, where he studied drama with George Pierce Baker and was a student in Baker's famous "47 Workshop" course. A member of the American Theater Laboratory, Daly occassionally acted in professional theaters and served as director of theaters in various parts of the country. Daly also worked as a copy-writer and editor for N. W. Ayer, Standard Oil Company of Ohio, and the WPA California. Works by Daly include The Guilty Sun (1926), One Season Shattered (1936), and Poems: 1923-1943 (1943).
Biographical information taken from The Dryden Press publicity for Poems: 1923-1943 (1943).
Scope and Contents
The James Joseph Daly papers contain correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and professional activity of poet and playwright James Joseph Daly. Correspondence in the collection consists chiefly of incoming correspondence from writers, journal editors, publishers, and others, but also includes drafts and carbons of outgoing letters and writings and enclosures. Correspondents include Elizabeth Ames at Yaddo, Kenneth Burke, John Cheever, Padraic Colum, Malcolm Cowley at The New Republic, James T. Farrell, Robinson Jeffers, Alfred Kreymborg, Haniel Long, Archibald MacLeish, Henry Miller, Kenneth Rexroth, Lennox Robinson, and Thornton Wilder. Writings in the collection include drafts of plays, poems, and other writings, such as short essays, sketches, scenes of plays, reviews, notes, and school papers. Personal papers feature notebooks and material relating to the theater, including manuscript material, correspondence, and printed material, such as playbills and clippings.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1919-1949. II. Writings, 1921-1943. III. Personal Papers, 1916-1945.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; Ames, Elizabeth; Burke, Kenneth, 1897-1993; Cheever, John, 1912-1982; Colum, Padraic, 1881-1972; Cowley, Malcolm, 1898-1989; Daly, James Joseph, 1901-1945; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962; Kreymborg, Alfred, 1883-1966; Long, Haniel, 1888-1956; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980; Rexroth, Kenneth, 1905-1982; Robinson, Lennox, 1886-1958; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975; Yaddo (Artists' colony)
- Correspondence, 1919-1949; Series I; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence consists chiefly of incoming correspondence from writers, journal editors, publishers, and others, but also includes drafts and carbons of outgoing letters and writings and enclosures.
  Correspondents include Elizabeth Ames at Yaddo, Kenneth Burke, John Cheever, Padraic Colum, Malcolm Cowley at The New Republic, James T. Farrell, Robinson Jeffers, Alfred Kreymborg, Haniel Long, Archibald MacLeish, Henry Miller, Kenneth Rexroth, Lennox Robinson, and Thornton Wilder.
  - "A" general, 1923-1944, undated (Box 1)
  - "B" general, 1922-1944, undated (Box 1)
  - Baker, George Pierce, 1926 July 23 (Box 1)
  - Burke, Kenneth, 1935-1943, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Business Correspondence, 1937, undated (Box 1)
  - "C" general, 1926-1936, undated (Box 1)
  - "D-E" general, 1926-1943, undated (Box 1)
  - Daly, Margo, 1944; 2 (Box 1)
  - Engel, A. Lehman, 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - "F" general, 1933-1944, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "G" general, 1931-1943, undated (Box 1)
  - "H" general, 1933-1944, undated (Box 1)
  - Harcourt, Brace, and Company, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - "I-K" general, 1924-1944, undated (Box 2)
  - "L" general, 1939, undated (Box 2)
  - The Little Theatre, 1927 May 17 (Box 2)
  - Long, Haniel, 1919-1941, undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - "M" general, 1920-1937, undated (Box 2)
  - Miller, Henry, 1944 (Box 2)
  - "N-Q" general, 1924-1939, undated (Box 2)
  - "R" general, 1931-1945, undated (Box 2)
  - "S" general, 1934-1940, undated (Box 2)
  - "T-V" general, 1935, undated (Box 2)
  - "W-Z" general, 1928-1944, undated (Box 2)
  - Letters re. James Daly's poetry; copyrights, 1933-1942 (Box 2)
  - Letters and Clippings re. James Daly and his work, 1922-1942 (Box 2)
- Writings, 1921-1943; Series II; 1.88; (4 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Plays, Poetry and Other Writings, and Writings by Others.
  Series II. contains writings by Daly and others. The Plays subseries consists chiefly of theatrical scripts and work by Daly. Poems and Other Writings are essentially unsorted writings, with a mix of drafts of poems and other writings, including short essays, sketches, scenes of plays, reviews, notes, and school papers, as well as some correspondence and other material, such as printed ephemera and clippings.
  - Plays
    - Adam Urbas, 1928-1941, undated; 3 (Box 3)
    - The Ballad of Judas Iscariot, undated (Box 3)
    - Black Night, undated (Box 3)
    - Blue Roses, undated (Box 3)
    - Crucible, 1921-1922, undated; 3 (Box 3)
    - Discovery, undated (Box 3)
    - Essential Zenkrad, [1920s] (Box 3)
    - From This Dark Soil, 1924-1930; 3 (Box 3)
    - The Golden Living, undated (Box 3)
    - Heaven Helps Him, undated (Box 3)
    - Misalliance, undated (Box 4)
    - The Moon Bride, 1943, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - North Wanderer, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - The Other Things, undated (Box 4)
    - Paris Bound, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - Porcelain Cups, undated (Box 4)
    - Relic Quade, [circa 1937] (Box 4)
  - Poetry and Other Writings
    - Poems, 1939, undated; 3 (Box 5)
    - Poems with comments by Charles Harris, 1919-1925 (Box 5)
    - Poems and other writings, 1920-1944, undated; 6 (Box 5)
    - Poems and other writings, 1920-1944, undated; 6 (Box 6)
    - Poems-Reviews, 1923-1943 (Box 6)
    - Unidentified writings, undated (Box 6)
    - Unsorted letters, notes, and writings, 1930-1944, undated (Box 6)
    - Copyrights, 1926-1947 (Box 6)
  - Writings by Others
    - Bodeen, Dewitt: "The Trojan Women", undated (Box 7)
    - Fletcher, James Gould: "Can Communism be Colonial?", 1935 September (Box 7)
    - Greenhood, David: "Felicities", undated (Box 7)
    - Long, Haniel: Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 7)
    - Molar, Ferencz: "The Swan", 1929-1944, undated; 2 (Box 7)
    - Whitsett, George: "The Sleeper", undated (Box 7)
- Personal Papers, 1916-1945; Series III; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III. Personal Papers contain notebooks, material relating to the theater, and a small amount of other material. Theater materials include printed ephemera, such as playbills and clippings containing reviews of plays, manuscript material, and correspondence.
  - Artwork, undated (Box 7)
  - Decker orders, undated (Box 7)
  - Employees' Publication: 23rd Annual National Safety Congress, 1934 October (Box 7)
  - Natal charts, undated (Box 7)
  - Newspaper clippings re Rose O'Neill, 1943-1944
  - Notebooks, 1920-1928, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - Notebooks, undated; 14 (Box 8)
  - Notebooks, 1916, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Puzzles, etc., 1925, undated (Box 9)
  - School exam books, 1919 December 19 (Box 9)
  - School notes, undated (Box 9)
  - The Sohioan, printed version, 1933-1934 (Box 9)
  - Theater material, 1918-1945, undated; 11 (Box 10)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Envelope from Poems with comments by Charles Harris (In Series II), undated (Box 11 (oversize))
  - Clipping from Poems and other writings (In Series II), 1938 June 26 (Box 11 (oversize))
  - Clipping from Poems and other writings (In Series II), 1938 June 26 (Box 11 (oversize))
  - Clippings from Unsorted letters, notes, and writings (In Series II), 1937, undated (Box 11 (oversize))
  - Newspaper clippings re Rose O'Neill (In Series III), 1943-1944 (Box 11 (oversize))
  - Clippings from Theater material (In Series III), undated (Box 11 (oversize))